<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hereafter ensueth the auncient seuerall customes, of the seuerall mannors of Stebbunhuth, and Hackney, within the countie of Middlesex which were perused, viewed &amp; approued, by the lorde of the said mannors, and by all the copieholde tenants of the said seueral mannors, manie yeeres past, and which customes be now againe newelie and fullie considered off, ratified, allowed, and approued, by the right Honourable, Henrie L. Wentworth, lord of the saide seueral mannors, as in the seuerall articles &amp; agreements hereafter following are expressed, the x. day of Nouember. 1587. and in the 29. yeere of the raigne of our Soueraigne Ladie Elizabeth, by the grace of God, Queene of England, Fraunce and Ireland, defender of the faith.</title>
            <title>Auncient severall customes, of the severall mannors of Stebbunhuth, and Hackney, 1587.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12960</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23252</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120936</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856127</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856127</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21650</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12960)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21650)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1035:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hereafter ensueth the auncient seuerall customes, of the seuerall mannors of Stebbunhuth, and Hackney, within the countie of Middlesex which were perused, viewed &amp; approued, by the lorde of the said mannors, and by all the copieholde tenants of the said seueral mannors, manie yeeres past, and which customes be now againe newelie and fullie considered off, ratified, allowed, and approued, by the right Honourable, Henrie L. Wentworth, lord of the saide seueral mannors, as in the seuerall articles &amp; agreements hereafter following are expressed, the x. day of Nouember. 1587. and in the 29. yeere of the raigne of our Soueraigne Ladie Elizabeth, by the grace of God, Queene of England, Fraunce and Ireland, defender of the faith.</title>
                  <title>Auncient severall customes, of the severall mannors of Stebbunhuth, and Hackney, 1587.</title>
                  <author>Wentworth, Henry Wentworth, Lord, 1588-1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>T. Snodham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1610]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Auncient customes to be obserued.</note>
                  <note>This edition printed in black letter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stepney (London, England : Manor) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hackney (London, England : Manor) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="legal_document">
            <pb facs="tcp:21650:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21650:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Hereafter enſueth the auncient <hi>ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cuſtomes, of the ſeuerall Mannors of</hi> Steb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunhuth, <hi>and</hi> Hackney,<note place="margin">Stebbun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huth, Hackney.</note> 
               <hi>within the Countie of</hi> Middleſex, which were peruſed, viewed &amp; approued, by <hi>the Lorde of the ſaid Mannors, and by all the Copieholde</hi> Tenants of the ſaid ſeueral Mannors, manie yeeres paſt, and which cuſtomes be now againe newelie and fullie conſidered off, ratified, allowed, and approued, by the right Honorable, <hi>Henrie</hi> L. <hi>Wentworth,</hi> Lord of the ſaide ſeuerall Mannors, and all the Copieholde Tenantes of the ſaid Mannors, as in the ſeuerall Articles &amp; agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hereafter following are expreſſed, the x. day of Nouember. 1587. And in the 29. yeere of the raigne of our Soueraigne Ladie <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by the grace of God, Queene of England, Fraunce and Ireland, defender of the faith.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Nprimis,</hi> by the cuſtomes of the ſaid Mannours, al the Copieholde Landes and Tenementes of the ſaide Mannours, and of euerie of them, be, and alwaies haue beene auncient copieholdes of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance in Feeſimple, according to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall cuſtomes of the ſaide Mannours, and of euerie of them, of which the ſame been ſeuerally holden, except ſuth parts and parcells of the ſaid Mannours, or of either of them, being of the demeaſne lands, and of the waſts of the ſaid man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
<pb facs="tcp:21650:2"/> and of either of them, which haue not beene graunted out by the Lorde or Lords of the ſame, to holde by coppie of Court roll, but ſithens the beginning of the raigne of the queenes Maieſtie that nowe is, which partes and parcells ſo graunted to holde by coppie of court roll. are and be excepted, and are ment to bee excepted out of theſe Articles, ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and agreement, and alſo all other the landes, tenements, and hereditamentes, mentioned and ſpecified in the ſeconde ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dule to theſe preſents annexed, which are and ſhalbe of no other validitie and force then they ſhoulde haue beene of, if theſe articles and agreements had neuer been made. And all coppies haue beene tyme out of minde, and bee made to holde of the Lord by the rodde, according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the ſaide mannours, by the rents, cuſtomes, ſuts and ſeruices, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore due and accuſtomed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2 Item,</hi> the rentes of all the tenements, both freeholders, and coppieholders, which holde anie meſwages, cotages, lands, tenements, or hereditaments of the ſaide mannours, or of anie of them is
<pb facs="tcp:21650:2"/> yeerelie payable at the feaſt of ſaint Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaell Tharchangell, to the Lorde and his heires, the ſame to be collected by Reeues of the ſaid mannors, to be yeere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie choſen, as heereafter is expreſſed, and all and euerie the coppieholde Tenants, ſhal hereafter pay ſo much rent as anie of them haue paid within two yeeres laſt paſt for their ſeuerall coppieholds, &amp; that if anie one of the ſaide coppieholds, for the which anie intire quitrent is nowe paide, ſhall come into ſeuerall hands, the ſaide rent ſhall be apporcioned by tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3 Item,</hi> all the coppieholde Tenants, which now be, or heereafter for the time being ſhalbe, ought to appeare yeerelie at two generall Courts holden for the ſaid mannors, or for either of them. And alſo ſo many of them at al other ſet or apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Courts, ſet, appointed, or kept, or to be ſet, apointed, or kept, for the ſaid man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, or for either of them, or for the Lord or Lords of the ſaid manors, or of either of them as ſhall be warned therevnto by the Reeue or his ſufficient deputy for the time being, and they to doe their ſutes
<pb facs="tcp:21650:3"/> and ſeruices according to their tenures, except they be eſſoyned, lycenced, or haue ſome other lawful excuſe, vpon the paine heereafter following, which generall courts haue beene commonlie kept, and are to be kept yeerelie thone of them the Tueſdaie next after Lowe Sundaye, &amp; thother about the feaſt of Saint An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewe the apoſtle, vpon reaſonable war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4 Item,</hi> if anie of the cuſtomarie or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieholde tenants of the ſaid Mannors, or of either of them, doe or ſhall make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault in their appearaunce at anie of the ſaide two generall courts to which their ſutes ſhall be due, or if ſuch copieholde tenants as ſhallbe eſpeciallie warned to appeare at anie of the ſaide ſette Courts in forme aforeſaide, yeerelie to be holden, doe make default, to which the ſaide ſute is or ſhalbe due, and warning openlie giuen in the pariſh churches within the ſaid Mannours, of the daie and place of the holdyng of the ſame generall courts, &amp; vpon ſpeciall warning to be giuen for the ſaid ſeuerall ſet Courts, that then they that ſhall ſo make default, except
<pb facs="tcp:21650:3"/> they be eſſoyned, or haue ſome other law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or reaſonable excuſe, ſhall be amerſed by the homage of the ſaide Court or anie of them, which amerciement ſhall bee taxed by two Afferrours of the ſayde Court. That is to ſay, by two Tenants of the homage, whereof the Steward of the ſaide Mannours, or of either of them for the time being, hath alwaies vſed to chooſe, and ſhal chooſe one for the Lorde, and the reſidue of the homage then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, haue choſen, and heareafter ſhall chooſe the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>5 Item,</hi> if anie Tenant bee Summoned to appeare at anie ſet Court or Courts to bee holden within the ſaide Mannors, or in anie of them, and doth appeare vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſaide Sommons, he ought, and is to haue for his paines iiij. d. and his dinner, or viij. d. and no dinner, which ought and is by the ſaide cuſtome to bee paid by ſuch perſon or perſons who ſhall bee the cauſe that anie ſuch Tenants do appeare for his or their matter, ſo it bee not for any matter or cauſe that concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth an inquirie or preſentment to be made concerning the Lord for the time
<pb facs="tcp:21650:4"/> being, his heires or aſſignes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>6 Item,</hi> the Copieholde Tenants of the ſaide Mannours, and of eyther of them, ought to haue euerie of them like allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce vpon euerie viewe by them to bee made, and vpon euerie partition by them to be made, or vppon other Summons to appeare betwixt Tenaunt and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, when they be appointed therevnto by precept from the Stewarde of the ſaid mannors, or of either of them for the time being, or by his ſufficient deputie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>7 Item,</hi> the homage of the Court of the ſaide Mannours, or of anie of them, may appoint ſixe or ſeuen Tenants vppon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anie complaint to them made by anie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons being Tenantes of the ſaide mannours, or of either of them in open Court, that he or they be wronged by any incrochme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or anie other annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, which Tenauntes ſhall after the ſaide Court, viewe the ſame incroch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, annoyance, and impediment, or place whereof anie ſuch complaint ſhall be made, and therevpon to preſent or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the ſame by a day to the Stewarde, or to the homage at the next generall
<pb facs="tcp:21650:4"/> Court, that there may be ſette a paine or amerciement, or both, for the ſame, by the homage at the ſaide next Court, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the qualitie of the offence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>8 Item,</hi> the homage of euerie of the ſaide Mannours, are to make preſentment at euerie general Court to be holden for the ſaid Mannours, or for either of them, of all the cuſtomarie or coppieholde Tenauntes, that they ſhall knowe ſhall haue died, after the Court then laſt paſt, or at any time before the ſaid court, whoſe deathes were not then found and preſented, which ſhall haue holden anie cuſtomarie or coppieholde Landes or Tenementes of the ſaid Mannours, or of either of them. And alſo as neere as they can, preſent what Landes they dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeazed of, and alſo of what eſtate, and when he died, and who is the next heire or heyres to the ſame perſon or perſons ſo dying ſeazed, and of what age or ages the ſaide heyre or heyres ſhall then bee off as neere as they can.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>9 Item,</hi> likewiſe the homage ought to preſent the deathes of freeholders, and
<pb facs="tcp:21650:5"/> when they dyed, and who bee their next heyres, and the ages of their heires which helde anie Lands or Tenements of the ſaide mannours, or of either of them, and the nature of their tenures, ſo neere as they can, to thintent the Lorde may haue his reliefe, which is but the value of one yeeres quitrent of the Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holden of the ſaide mannours, or of either of them by Socage tenure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>10 Item,</hi> if the homage at anie of the ſaide Courts of either of the ſaide man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, ſhall not knowe who is next heire or heyres to anie of the ſaide cuſtomarye Tenauntes ſo dying ſeazed, when they ſhall make their preſentments, that then they ſhall make their preſentment ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and then vppon the ſaide pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, at the next generall Court af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Stewarde of the ſaide mannors or of eyther of them, or his deputie for the time being, within which the ſaide pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment ſhall ſo bee made, ſhall cauſe a Proclamation to be made in open court, to thintent euerie ſuch heyre or heyres may haue knowledge to come and take vp the Landes and tenements of his or
<pb facs="tcp:21650:5"/> their aunceſtours, and ſo the Steward or his deputie, ſhall cauſe a Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to bee made from generall Court to generall Court, vntill three open and publique Proclamations bee made in ful Court, at three ſeuerall generall courts, which generall Courts, by the ſaid cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome are vſed to bee holden commonlie one halfe yeere after another or there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, ſo that from the firſt Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the laſt, is full neere one yeere and a halfe, which is about full two yeeres from the preſentment made by the ſayde Homage of the dying ſeazed, of the ſayde laſt Tenaunt, vnto the laſt Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and if there ſhall come no heire to the ſaide Lands or Tenements, before the ende of the ſaide three Proclamations, to make his clayme, and prooue himſelfe to the Homage of the ſaide Court, in ſuche ſort as they ſhall allowe off, to bee the next heire of the whole blood, to the ſaide Tenaunte deceaſed, or to haue title to the Lande and tenements, nor to ſhewe and prooue as aforeſaid, who is or ought to be the next heire of the whole bloud to the ſaide Tenaunt deceaſed, or next heire
<pb facs="tcp:21650:6"/> expectant vpon anie eſtate determined, then the Lorde of the ſaide Mannours, or of either of them for the time being, ſhal and may after the ſaide three Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſo to bee made, ſeaze the Landes and Tenements, which was the ſayde perſons ſo dying ſeaſed, whoſe next heire or ſuch as ſhall haue title therevnto can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee founde, or ſhall not come and make his or their claime and proofe as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaide, and then to take the iſſues and profites thereof vnto his owne vſe, vntill ſuch perſon or perſons come that ſhall prooue him or them next heire or heyres to the ſaide perſon or perſons ſo dying ſeazed, and if none ſhal come within three yeeres next after the thirde and laſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation to bee made as aforeſaid, that ſhall and can conueigh and proue him or them to bee next heire or heires of the whole bloud, or ſhewe and prooue who is or ought to be next heire, or to haue ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, as next in remaynder or reuertion as aforeſaide. That then the ſaide Landes and Tenementes bee forfayted, or ſhall eſcheate vnto the Lorde of the ſaide
<pb facs="tcp:21650:6"/> Mannour or Mannours, for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, except that if the ſaid Lands &amp; tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhall or ought immediatly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, remaine, reuert, or come to any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man couert, or infant, within the age of xxi. yeeres, or to any perſon or perſons not of <hi>Sane memoriae,</hi> or that ſhall not bee within the Realme, at the time of the death of the ſaid laſt Tenaunt dying ſo ſeazed, that then the Lorde for the tyme being, ſhall haue but the profites of the ſaide Landes and Tenementes, vntill ſuch perſons or their heires, ſhall come and make their claime as aforeſaide, ſo the ſaide clayme be made within fiue yeeres by the ſaide woman or her heires next after the death of her ſaid huſband, or by ſuch perſon being within age, or his heires within fiue yeeres next after he ſhall or ſhould accompliſh his full age of twentie one yeeres, and by the heyre of ſuch perſon of <hi>Non ſane memoriae,</hi> within fiue yeeres after the death of his ſaid aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour, or by the ſaid perſon or his heyres that ſhall ſo be out of the Realme within fiue yeeres after he ſhall returne, or if hee ſhall not returne within fiue yeeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21650:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>11 Item,</hi> women are to haue no dowers of anie cuſtomarie Landes or Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments within the Mannours aforeſaid, nor in anie of them, nor menne to haue anie eſtate as Tenantes by the curteſie of Englande.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>12 Item,</hi> if a man or woman ſhalbe ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed of anie cuſtomarie Landes or Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes holden of the ſaide Mannours, or of either of them, of an eſtate of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, and ſhal haue iſſue two Sonnes or three Sonnes, or more, or hauing no Sonnes, ſhall haue diuers Daughters, or hauing neyther Sonnes nor Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſhall haue diuers collaterall heires, they ſhall be all coheyres to their ſayde Father, Mother, or other Aunceſtour touching the ſaide cuſtomarie Landes and tenements, according to the cuſtome of Gauelkinde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>13 Item,</hi> if a man or woman die ſeazed as aforeſaide, of any cuſtomarie Lands or Tenementes of anie eſtate of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce holden of the ſaide Mannours, or of anie of them, and ſhall haue iſſue two or three ſonnes or more, whereof one or
<pb facs="tcp:21650:7"/> two or more of them ſhalbe married, and ſhall haue iſſue in the life of their father or mother, and ſhall die before his or their ſaide Father or Mother, or hauing no ſonnes, ſhall haue diuers daughters, whereof one or more ſhalbe married, and haue iſſue, and die in the life of the father or mother. That then the ſaide iſſue ſhall inherite, and bee coheire with the ſayde ſonne or ſonnes, or daughter, that ſhall ſuruiue his or her ſaide father or mother that ſo ſhall die ſeazed, as is aforeſaide, whether the ſaide iſſue be Male or Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, according to the cuſtome of Gauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>14 Item,</hi> if anie perſon or perſons, dye ſeazed as aforeſaide, and ſhall leaue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him neyther ſonne nor daughter, then the next of his or their kinne being of whole bloud, ſhalbe heyre or heyres to the ſaide perſon or perſons ſo dying ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, that is to ſay, his or their brother, or brothers children, or childers children, according to the cuſtome of Gauelkinde and ſo foorth, as long as anie of that iſſue ſhalbe on liue, being of the whole bloud, and in default of ſuche iſſue, the
<pb facs="tcp:21650:8"/> Siſters and Siſters children, according to the cuſtome of Gauelkind, and ſo forth as long as anie iſſue ſhalbe on liue, and being of the whole bloud, and for lacke of ſuch iſſue, the Vnckles and their iſſues, being of the whole bloud ſo long as anie iſſue ſhalbe liuing. And no default of ſuch iſſue, the Aunts and their children, ſo long as anie ſhalbe liuing of the whole bloud, &amp; for lacke of ſuch iſſue, the next of kinne of the whole bloud, according to the cuſtome of Gauelkinde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>15 Item,</hi> If anie perſon ſo dying ſeazed as aforeſaide, without iſſue of his bodie, and hauing diuers brothers of the whole bloud, whereof the one or ſome of them ſhall haue beene married, and ſhall haue iſſue, and after iſſue had, ſhall die before the ſaide brother dying ſeazed, as aforeſaide. That then the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues of the ſaide brother or brothers ſo dying before him that died ſeazed, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaide, ſhall ioyne and be coheyre with the brother that ſuruiueth the brother that ſo died ſeazed as aforeſaide, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſaid iſſue be Males or Females. But Males and Females of one venter, can not ioyne to be coheires together, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:21650:8"/> that the courſe of diſcentes is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued by the ſaide cuſtome, according to the cuſtome and nature of landes in Gauelkinde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>16 Item,</hi> likewiſe ſhall the iſſue of the daughter that ſhall die in the life of the Father or Mother, be coheire with the Aunt that liueth, being of the whole bloud.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>17 Item,</hi> likewiſe ſhall the Vnckles, and the Vnckles brothers children, being of the whole bloud, be coheires together as aforeſaide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>18 Item,</hi> likewiſe ſhall the Aunts, and the Aunts ſiſters children, ioyne and be coheires as aforeſaid, and ſo forth of all further degrees of all collaterall heires, being of the whole bloud, which may conueigh themſelues to be anie Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins and heires of the whole bloud to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie perſon or perſons dying ſeazed, of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the foreſaide cuſtomarie Landes or Tenements, according to the cuſtome of Gauelkind.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21650:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>19 Item,</hi> by the cuſtomes of the ſaide ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Mannours, euerie coppieholder of inheritaunce in fee ſimple, may ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his ſaide coppieholde Landes and Tenements, or anie part or parcell ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnto any perſon or perſons, and to his or their heires for euer, or to his or their heires, of his or their bodies, or any other waies intaile, or for life or liues, or yeres, or to anie perſon or perſons, and to their heires, to thintent the ſaide coppieholde Tenante may declare his laſt Will and Teſtament vppon the ſame Lands and Tenements, or to anie other vſe or vſes, vnleſſe it bee to anie corporation or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, or bodies politique or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate. And euerie coppieholder intayle, for life, liues or yeeres, of anie of the ſaide Mannours, may in like manner by the cuſtomes of the ſaide Manuours, and of euerie of them, ſurrender their coppie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde Landes, or anie part thereof, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature of their eſtates, ſo the ſame ſurrender be made according to the cuſtome concerning ſurrenders, as heereafter enſueth. And all the ſame perſons to whoſe vſe euerie ſuch ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:21650:9"/> ſhalbe made, are to haue their copies made to hold of the Lord by the Rodde, according to the Cuſtome of the ſaide Manours, whereof they beene ſeuerally holden, by the rentes, cuſtomes, ſutes, and ſeruices therefore due and accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, vpon euery of which ſurre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, the fine and fines for the ſame heereafter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed is by the ſaid cuſtoms to be paid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>20 Item,</hi> By the cuſtome of the ſayde Mannours, and of euerie of them, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſurrender taken out of the Court by the Headborow or Reeue, or his depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and in the preſence of ſixe cuſtomarie Tenaunts of the ſaide Mannours, of which the ſaide Landes or Tenements ſurrendred ſhalbe percell, witneſſing the ſame ſurrender of anie perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of his or their cuſtomarie Landes or Tenements holden of the ſaid Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, or of either of them, and being of the full age of one and twentie yeeres or vpwardes, except women coouert bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and ſuch as are not of perfect minde, to the vſe of any perſon or perſons, ſhalbe as good as if it were taken in open court by the ſaid Steward of the ſaide Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
<pb facs="tcp:21650:10"/> or of anie of them, ſo that ſuch ſurrenders be by Thomage preſented as haereafter followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>21 Item,</hi> By the ſaide cuſtome, no wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man being couert barron, can make any good ſurrender of her Landes and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementes holden of the ſaide Mannors, or of either of them, eyther by the handes of the Reeue or his deputie, or by the handes of the Headeborow, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the ſaide ſixe Tenaunts, ſauing in time of extremity of ſickeneſſe or death, in either of which caſes, ſhe may by the ſaide Cuſtome together with her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande, ſurrender her ſaide Landes and Tenements, holden of the ſaide Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, or of either of them, by the hands of the Reeue or Headeborowe, and ſixe Tenaunts, and if anie ſuch woman couert barron ſo ſurrendring, doe after that recouer her health, and doe not at the next generall Court then following, ratifie and confirme the ſame before the Stewarde or his deputie, in the preſence of the Homage, that then the ſame ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render is to bee voide. And all ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders made by anie woman couert bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron
<pb facs="tcp:21650:10"/> otherwiſe then in extremitie of ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or death, as is aforeſaide be voide, except ſuch women couert barron, bee ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examined before the Stewarde of the ſaide Mannours, or of anie of them, or his ſufficient deputie, as heereafter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>22 Item,</hi> That all ſurrenders taken ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Reeue or his deputie, or by the Headborowe, for the time being, and in the preſence of ſixe cuſtomarie tenants, ought to be by the Homage preſented at the generall Court holden for the ſayde Mannours, after the taking thereof, or within one yeere and a day next after the taking of the ſame, if anie ſuch generall Court bee holden within the yeere and the day after the ſame ſurrender ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or elſe if no ſuch generall Courte bee holden within the yeere and the day, then to bee by the ſame Homage pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented at the next generall Courte to be holden after the ſame yeere and daie, and then to be as good a ſurrender, as anie ſurrender taken in open Courte, or elſe all ſurrenders taken by the ſaide Reeue or his deputie, or by the ſaid Headborow,
<pb facs="tcp:21650:11"/> and in the preſence of ſixe Tenauntes, and not preſented by the ſaide homage, in maner and forme aforeſayd to be void.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>23. Item,</hi> The homage by the ſaide cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, muſt write <hi>Billa vera</hi> vppon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſurrender by them preſented, when they finde the ſame ſurrenders agreeable to the cuſtome, and alſo vppon euerie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their preſentmentes they ſhall make <hi>Billa vera,</hi> when they be agreeable to the ſaide cuſtome, or elſe if the ſayde homage receaue anie ſurrender, or other billes to them exhibited, which be repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt to the cuſtome of the ſaide Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, or of either of them, they ſhall make vpon euerie ſuch ſurrender or bill, <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> or the like ſuperſcription, to thintent it may be knowen to be naught, or elſe returne ſuch naughtie ſurrenders or billes backe againe to the parties that exhibited the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>24 Item,</hi> By the cuſtome of the ſayde Mannours, and of euerie of them, euerie woman being couert barron, of the age of one and twentie yeeres or vpwardes, hauing anie cuſtomarie Landes or Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementes
<pb facs="tcp:21650:11"/> to her or her heires, or for life, liues, or yeeres, and holden of the ſayde Mannours, or of either of them, may to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with her huſbande, by the hands of the ſaide Stewarde, or of his ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent deputie, ſurrender al her ſaid Lands and Tenementes, intereſt, or terme of yeeres, to the vſe of her ſaide huſband, or to any other perſon or perſons, at their will and pleaſure, ſo as ſhe bee ſolie and ſecretlie examined before the Stewarde or his ſufficient deputie, according to the auncient cuſtome vſed in that caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>25 Item,</hi> That all ſurrenders taken out of the court by the Steward of the ſaid Mannours, or of anie of them, or by his ſufficient deputie, of anie perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, being of the full age of one and twentie yeeres or more, of anie of their cuſtomarie Landes and Tenementes holden of the ſaide Mannours, or of ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, be good by the cuſtome of the ſaide Mannours, and of eyther of them, and the ſame to be publiſhed and notified to the homage at the next gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Courte.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21650:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>26 Item,</hi> By the cuſtome of the ſaide Mannours, and of euerie of them, all ſurrenders at anie time heeretofore ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or heereafter to be taken by the ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the ſaide Mannours, or of ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, or by his ſufficient deputie, out of the Courte of anie cuſtomarie Landes or Tenementes holden of the ſaide Mannours, or of either of them, of anie perſon or perſons, being of full age of xxi yeeres as aforeſaide, being entred into the Court rolls, of the Court next going before the taking of the ſame ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renders, although ſuch ſurrenders were taken diuers daies, weekes, or monethes after the ſame Courte, are and ſhalbe good and of force, by the cuſtome of the ſaide Mannours, and of euerie of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>27. Item,</hi> By the cuſtome of the ſaide Mannours, and of euerie of them, the Lorde or Lordes of the ſaide Mannors, or of eyther of them, ought to haue at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie admiſſion of anie one perſon, or more, vppon a diſcent, and at euerie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and of anie one perſon, onelie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a ſurrender, or alienation to be made of euerie acre of Lande or grounde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:21650:12"/> Coppieholde, xvi. d. for a fine, and ſo after that rate, and no more, and if anye more then one bee admitted vppon a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, then to paie for euerie one ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, more then one halfe a fine, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to haue in like ſort for a ſingle fine for a meſwage being Copiehold, xiii. S. iiii. d. and for a Tenement being Coppiehold, x. s. and for a Cotage being coppieholde, which ſhall not be letten for aboue iii. li. by the yeere, xx. d. and for a Cotage being woorth aboue iii. li. by the yeere to be let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, to paye fine as before for a Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and theſe fines to bee ſette downe in their ſeuerall coppies, and if anie que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion ariſe about the decerning which be meſſwage, and which be Tenements, the ſame, by the ſame cuſtome is to bee tried by the preſentment of the homage, &amp; that the Lorde of the ſaid Mannors, and of either of them, ſhall allowe of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſurrender made by anie Coppiehol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, according to theſe articles, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made or committed anie cauſe of forfaiture, contrarie to the cuſtomes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in theſe articles, and ſhall for the fine aforeſaide, graunt the ſaide coppie,
<pb facs="tcp:21650:13"/> holdes, according to the ſaide ſurrender, and admitte ſuch perſons to whome the ſame ſurrender ſhall ſo bee made, or to whome theſe Landes or Tenementes ſhall ſo diſcende accordinglie, and if the ſaide Lorde ſhall refuſe ſo to admit, yet the ſaide perſons to whome the ſaid ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renders ſhalbe made, or to whome the ſaide Lande and Tenementes of right ought to diſcende, remayne, or come, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their fine, or tendring the ſame as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaide, ſhall quietlie holde and enioye the ſaide Coppie holde in like ſort, as if he or they were lawfullie admitted vnto the ſame, and not otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>28 Item,</hi> By the cuſtome, if anie manne make a ſurrender, onelie to the intent to make his wife a Ioynter, and to none other purpoſe, then the fine of the ſame is but halfe ſo much as it is vpon other ſurrenders, alienations, or vpon a dying ſeazed as aforeſaide. And the like cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome is to be obſerued, where the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande and wife make a ſurrender of the Landes of the wife, to the ende onelie to make an eſtate thereof to the huſbande ioyntlie with his wife, and likewiſe by
<pb facs="tcp:21650:13"/> the ſaid cuſtome for euery Tenaunt that ſhalbe admitted in reuercion or remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der expectant, vpon the eſtate of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for life, in taile, or for yeres, graunted by copie, the ſame is but halfe ſo much as it is vppon other admittaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vpon alienacions, ſurrenders, or dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeazed, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>29 Item,</hi> Euery perſon that exhibiteth or deliuereth anie ſurrender or bill to the homage, ought to giue and paie to the ſame homage for euery ſuch ſurrender or bill iiii. d. And by the ſaid cuſtome euery of the ſaid ſixe tenants and alſo the head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough or Reue which ſhalbe at the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ani ſurre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders as aforeſaid, ought to haue iiii. d. a peece, being taken within the ſaid Mannours or in either of them. But if they goe out of the ſaid mannors or either of them for the taking of the ſame, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue viii. d. a peece, and their charges, if they ſhall goe farther of: and the partie that procureth the ſaid ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ought to giue to the ſayd Tenaunts iiii. d. beſides the ſaid fees, which iiii. d. is deliuered with the ſayd ſurrender, or elſe he that bringeth in the ſayde ſurrender
<pb facs="tcp:21650:14"/> without the ſayd iiii. d. ſhall pay it of his owne purſſe to the homage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>30 Item,</hi> if it chance at any time vpon the death of any copiholder or cuſtomarie te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ther is an heire or heires found and preſented by thomage, &amp; which after are admitted to the lands &amp; tenements of the ſaide copieholder, at which time no other heires were knowne, &amp; after it chanceth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one or other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth &amp; claimeth to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heire with the ſaid heire, which is admit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, then the homage ought thereof to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, &amp; if they finde his clayme true, they ought to preſent the ſame, &amp; then he ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be likewiſe admitted, and paye his fine, and haue his part of the premiſſes, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the former admiſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>31 Item,</hi> if any man be admitted to any poſſeſſion, or to any reuercion or remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ani la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds or tenemte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, whether they be to him deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, as it is ſuppoſed, or to him ſurre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred by ani other perſon, &amp; after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth another perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, who pretendeth a title to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole premiſſes, or to ani part therof, &amp; willeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> homage to enquire therof, in this caſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid homage is not bound thereof to enquire, but he or thei are driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his or their ſute or plaint
<pb facs="tcp:21650:14"/> whether his or their tytle be right or wrong, yet if he or they require y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> homage to find whether he or they wer the ſon or ſons of ſuch a one or not, and the homage knowing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he or they were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon or ſons of ſuch a one, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing the homage ought to preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but not to preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t whether he or they ought to haue the premiſſes or any part therof, to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which another per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is alredy admitted, but in ſuch caſe he or thei ſhalbe driuen to his or their ſute or plaint as aforeſaid, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> recouery of their ſaid right, if any right they haue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>32 Item,</hi> after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of euery perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a cuſtomary tenant of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid manors, or of either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the next heire ought to come &amp; take vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lands &amp; teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts wher of his aunceſtours ſo ſhall dye ſeazed, of what age ſoeuer he be of, &amp; if he be of the age of xiiii. yeeres or vpwards, he is to be admitted in his own perſon within a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t time after he is preſented, or elſe if he be vnder the age of xiiii. yeres, then to come &amp; take it vp by his Garden, vntil he be of thage of xiiii. yeres as aforeſaid, &amp; to pay for his fine according to the rates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, &amp; the garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pay but iii. s. iiii. d at the moſt, for his fine for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gardenſhip,
<pb facs="tcp:21650:15"/> or leſſe, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſcretion of the Steward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>33 Item,</hi> likewiſe euery perſon to whoſe vſe any of the ſaid lands or tenements be ſurrendred, ought alſo to come within a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient time after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame be preſented, &amp; take vp the ſame by himſelfe, if he be of age, &amp; to be admitted, as aforeſaid, and to pay his fine, or elſe buy his Garden, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and to take out his copie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>34 Item,</hi> if any of the ſaid heires, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enees, or gardeins, do not pay their fines within one moneth after the ſame fines be extracted, and the extracts deliuered to the Reeue or his deputie, for the gathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring therof, and by them or either of them demaunded, then it ſhalbe lawfull for the L. or Lords of the ſaid mannor or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours for the tyme being, or his or their officers, to diſtraine and auowe as for rents, and for want of diſtreſſe, to ſeaze the landes and tenements, for the which the ſaid fine or fines are to be paid, and to enioy the ſame to his or their owne vſe, vntill he or they ſhalbe fully ſatiſfied and paid the ſayd fine or fines, to be paide by him or them that ſo ought to pay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>35 Item,</hi> if any cuſtomary or copiholde tenaunt of the ſaide Mannours, or of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:21650:15"/> of them, ſhall not pay his rents for his copiehold, for which the ſame is due, and demaunded by the ſaid Reeue, or his deputie, then it ſhalbe lawfull for the lord or lordes of the ſaide Mannour or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours for the tyme being, or his or their officers, to diſtraine and auowe, and for want of diſtreſſe, to ſeaze the lands and tenements, out of the which the ſame ought to be paid, &amp; to take &amp; to enioye the rents, iſſues &amp; profits, of the ſame, to his or their owne vſe, vntill he or they ſhalbe fully ſatiſfied &amp; paid the ſame rents, by him or them that ſo ought to pay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>36 Item,</hi> that when any Tenaunt dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, leauing his heire vnder thage of xiiii. yeeres, the cuſtome is, that the next of the kinne to whome the land and tenements can not deſcend, ſhall haue if he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it, the cuſtodie of the heire, &amp; of his landes and tenements committed vnto him, vntil he come to thage of xiiii. yeeres, and then he to chuſe his owne garden.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>37 Item,</hi> if any perſon or perſons be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to let his cuſtomarie Lands or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, to anie other perſon or perſons, and to their executors and aſſignes for terme of xxxi. yeeres or leſſe, the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:21650:16"/> perſon ſhall by the ſame cuſtome of the ſaid Mannours, vpon requeſt at a court holden, or to the Steward out of court, haue a licence by him or them graunted, paying for a fine to the lord after the rate of iiii. d. for euery yeere ſo vnto him graun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, and no more, for ſo many yeeres as he the ſame requireth, not exceeding xxxi. yeeres. Neuertheleſſe, by the ſaide cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, it ſhalbe lawfull for any perſon or perſons to let his cuſtomarie landes and tenements to anie perſon and perſons, and to their executors or aſſignes, for the terme of three yeeres, or leſſe, by writing, or by word, without licence to him to be graunted, and without paying any fine to the Lord, or incurring any forfaiture or ſeiſure for the ſame, ſo the ſame leaſe do not exceed three yeeres, from the date and making thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>38 Item,</hi> The cuſtomes of the ſayde Mannours is, to giue to the Lorde vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the chaunge of euerie Lorde, tenne poundes, that is to ſaie, out of eache Mannour fiue pound, for the recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and acknowledging of the ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21650:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>39 Item,</hi> By the cuſtome of the ſayde Mannours and of either of them, the Homage of euerie of the ſayde Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, doe vſe yeerelie at the generall Court to be holden next after Michel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, to electe and chuſe ſeuerall Ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, for euerie of the ſaide Mannours, that is to ſaie, to elect and chuſe two cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomarie Tenauntes to beare the office of the Reeue, for eache of the ſaid Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, namely, he that was before in election, and one other to him, to the intent the Lord of the ſaid Mannours or of either of them, or his Stewarde, may appoint the one of them ſo elected, for one whole yeere, for eche of the ſaide Mannours, ſo he be appointed within that Mannour, of which he is a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt, and for the which he ſhalbe ſo choſen, which Reeue ſo beeing appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ought by the cuſtome of the ſaide Mannours, to take vppon him the ſaid Office, for one whole yeere then next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, to execute the ſame by him ſelfe, or his Deputie, for whome hee ſhall aunſwere, and to be ſubiect to accompt and aunſwere for the ſame, as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue bene accuſtomed to doe.
<pb facs="tcp:21650:17"/> And if a copieholder ſhalbe choſen to be the lordes Reelie, according to his turne, and refuſe to ſerue the ſaid office by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or by his deputie, being appointed thervnto, as aforeſaid, euery ſuch perſon ſo refuſing, within the ſayd Mannour of Hackney, ſhall pay for a fine vi. li. xiii. s. iiii. d. and euery ſuch perſon ſo refuſing, within the ſayd Mannour of Stebbun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huth, ſhall pay for a fine x. li. to the Lord of the ſayde Mannours, and the homage of either Mannours ſhalbe charged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time to chuſe an other Reeue, in place of him that ſo refuſeth, vntill ſuch time that one be choſen that ſhal and wil ſerue the ſayde office. And euery copie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder that ſhalbe choſen to the ſayde of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as his turne ſhall come about and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, ſhall pay the fines aforeſaid, for his refuſall. And if any copieholder that ſhall execute the ſayde office and doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to ſatiſfie and ſaye to the Lord ſuch rentes, fines, and amerciaments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he ſhalbe lawfully charged, or ſhall refuſe to accompte with the Lord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two monethes next yeerely after Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaehnas, hauing had the extracts for that yeere, by the ſpace of two monethes,
<pb facs="tcp:21650:17"/> euery ſuch Reeues Landes and Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, that ſhall refuſe to accompt and to pay the ſaid rents, fines, amercements and iſſues as aforeſaid, ſhalbe ſeazed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lordes handes, and the lord ſhall and may take to his owne vſe, the iſſues and profites of his ſaide landes and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, vntill he ſhall paie vnto the Lord the ſaide rentes, iſſues, fines and profits, and till he haue alſo ſatiſfied and paide the Lord for his ſaide offence: <hi>Viz.</hi> being Reeue of Hackney, vi. li. xiii. s. iiii. d and being Reeue of Stebbunhuth. x. li.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>40 Item,</hi> That euerie cuſtomarie Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt whoſe cuſtomarie landes or tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments holden of the ſaide Mannours, or of either of them be worth to be ſold ſo much money as one yeeres rent of aſſiſe, with the profites and proquiſits of the Courts of either of the ſaid Mannours, within the which he ſhalbe choſen that yeere, that he ſhalbe choſen Reeue of the ſaide Mannours, or of either of them ſhall amount vnto, by the eſtimation of the homage, ſhall beare the office of the Reeue for one whole yere, when his time and courſe doth come.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21650:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>41 Item,</hi> The Reeue of Stebbunhuth is bound by cuſtome yeerely to finde and make to the Lordes Steward and his counſeill three dinners, that is to ſay, one vpon the Leete daye, and the other two vppon the ſayde two generall Courte daies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>42 Item,</hi> Euerie of the ſaide Reeues is to be alowed of the ſaide Lord for the exerciſing of the ſaide office for one yeere, as foloweth: <hi>Viz.</hi> The Reeue of Steb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunhuth three pound, ſixe ſhillings, eight pence, and the Reeue of Hackney liii. s. iiii. d. and either of them a coate cloth and all other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities due and incident to the ſaide office.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>43 Item,</hi> By the cuſtome of the ſaide Mannours and of either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reeues of the ſaide Mannours and of either of them, ſhall at the next generall court af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his yeere of ſeruice expired, deliuer the Rentall, by which he made his accompt, to the Reeue that ſhall next ſucceede him, vpon paine to be amerced or fined by the homage, if he ſhall not ſo doe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21650:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>44 Item,</hi> By the cuſtome of the ſayde Mannours, and of either of them, all the cuſtomary tenaunts of the ſaide Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and of euery of them, may breake and digge their copiehold grounds hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the ſaide Mannours and of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them, at their pleaſure, and fell and cut downe their timber and wooddes growing, or that ſhall grow vppon the ſame, and conuert it to their beſt vſe and profit, and may alſo ſuffer their copie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold tenements and howſes to decaye, without incurring anie ſeiſure or forfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their eſtates therefore, and may take and pull downe their ſaide Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and erect or ſet them vp againe, either where they ſtoode before, or vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon anie other landes holden by coppie of court rowle of the ſaide Mannours, or of either of them.</p>
            <p>But they may not nor ſhall not take or pull them downe to ſett them or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie parte of them vppon theyr owne free holdes, or vppon the free holdes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anie other, or ſell or conuert them or any parte of them to their owne vſe, otherwiſe then is before limitted.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21650:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>45 Item,</hi> By the cuſtome of the ſaide Mannours, and of either of them, euery of the Lords Tenaunts may lop and ſhred all ſuch trees as grow before their howſes or tenements, vppon the waſt ground, and the ſame conuert to theyr owne vſe, without anie offence, ſo the ſaide trees ſtand for the defence of theyr houſes, yards, or gardens, and alſo may digge grauell, ſand, and lome, vppon the ſaide waſt ground, to build or repaire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of their copiehold tenements within the ſaid Mannours, or in either of them, without any licence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>46 Item,</hi> if any perſon or perſons being Tenaunt cuſtomarie, ſhall without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence by Indenture or other writing, or otherwiſe, let his ſaide cuſtomarie lands or Tenementes for terme of aboue three yeeres from the making thereof, it is a forfaiture of his eſtate, by the cuſtome of the ſaid Mannours, &amp; of either of them, being found by the homage, or elſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe lawfully and ſufficiently proued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>47 Item,</hi> For treaſon or felonie what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, that ſhalbe committed by any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieholder
<pb facs="tcp:21650:19"/> of the ſaid Mannours, or of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, for which he ſhalbe lawfully attainted, he ſhall forfaite his copieholde landes and tenements, and for all other offence or offences, acte or actes whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, for which a freeholder ought by law to forfaite his freeholde landes and tenements, there a copieholder of the ſaid Mannours or of either of them, ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faite as a freeholder ought to forfaite in the like caſe his free hold. And if a copie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder make a feoffament of his copie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, guift in taile, or leaſe for life or liues by deede or without deede, and liuery and ſeiſin therevpon, or ſhall ſuffer a recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie at the common lawe, leuey a fine or wilfully refuſe and deny to paie, doe or perfourme his rentes, fines, ſutes, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, or ſeruices at any time hereafter due to the lord or lords of the ſaid Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, or of either of them for their ſayd copieholds, the ſame wilfull refuſall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to the homage, by the othes of three cuſtomarie Tenaunts, with the Reeue or his deputie, (the ſaid tenaunts nor Reeue, nor his deputie being none of the Lords ſeruants,) And being found by the homage, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to be a forfaiture
<pb facs="tcp:21650:20"/> of his eſtate, whatſoeuer he ſhall haue at the time of any ſuch acte committed or done, inſomuch of his or their copiehold lande and tenements, as he ſhall haue made, committed, or done, anie ſuch acte, and onelie for ſo much of his ſaid Landes and Tenementes, out of the which the ſaide quitrent and other due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties is demaunded, and ſhalbe due, and wilfully denied by the ſayde Tenaunt or Tenaunts, as aforeſaide. Or if any copieholder ſhall in the Lords Court or elſe where, in any court of Record, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime to holde his ſaid copieholde lands and tenements of the Lord, or by plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the Lords court, or other court of recorde, claime their copieholdes to be free holdes, or pleade in anie Reall Accion at the Common Law in chiefe, as a free holde Tenaunt, or ſhall doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other acte or thing which ſhalbe a diſſeiſin or diſenheritance of the Lord or Lordes of the ſaide Mannours, or of either of them, their heires or aſſignes, (other then ſuch acts as in theſe articles are eſpecially diſpenſed withall.)</p>
            <p>That then hee ſhall forfayre the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:21650:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> landes and tenementes ſo diſclaiming to holde, or claiming to be free holde, or for which he ſhall pleade in Chiefe, or doe any ſuch other acte or thing as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide. Finally, the Lorde of the ſaide Mannours or of either of them, ſhall haue all ſuch other forfaitures, iſſues, profits and aduauntages of the ſaide co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piholdes that ſhall grow due to him by any Statute lawes of this realme, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not againſt and contrary to theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles and cuſtomes here expreſſely ſette downe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>48 Item,</hi> If any perſon or perſons ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing any eſtate of any copiehold lands or tenements holden of the ſaide Mannors or of either of them, for terme of life or liues, or for terme of yeres, or in the right of their wiues of any eſtate, although he or they ſhall doe any acte or actes during the time aforeſaide, in or vpon the ſayde copieholde landes or tenementes which might or ſhould bee contrarie to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the ſayde Mannours, or of either of them, the ſame Acte or Acts ſo beeinge done, ſhall not preiudice or bee hurtefull vnto the nexte perſonne
<pb facs="tcp:21650:21"/> or perſons to whome the ſaid cuſtomarie landes or tenementes ſhould or ought to remaine, reuert, or come, nor to the ſaide wife or her heires, not being partie, or conſenting to the ſaide acte or forfaiture, nor that the Lord of the ſaide Mannors or of either of them, ſhall take any longer aduantage, iſſues or profits of the ſame copiehold landes or tenements, then du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of ſuch eſtates as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, of the partie committing, doing, or conſenting to ſuch acte or acts, ſo that after his or their deceaſe or ſtates deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, the ſaide landes and tenements ſhall remaine, reuert, or come to the next perſon or perſons, or to ſuch perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons to whome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſhould haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or remained, or reuerted immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after ſuch eſtate or eſtates ended or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, as though there had bene no ſuch acte or actes done coutrarie to the ſaide cuſtome, by any ſuch perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>49 Item,</hi> By the cuſtome of the ſayde Mannours and of either of them, the particuler or priuate acte or actes of any cuſtomarie tenaunt or tenaunts of anie
<pb facs="tcp:21650:21"/> of the ſaide Mannours which ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be done wilfully, by or betweene them, or any of them and the Lord of the ſaide Mannours, and his Reeue or of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, contrarie to the cuſtome of the ſaide Mannours, neither doth nor ſhall extend to be conſtrued to be a breach of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auncient cuſtomes of the ſaid Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours or of either of them, to the hurt or preiudice of the reſt of the cuſtomarie te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunts, but of themſelues onely, doing the ſaid particular acte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>50 Item,</hi> that if any tenaunt for terme of life or liues onely, or for terme of yeres of cuſtomary lands, ſhal make any waſt, that then he ſhalbe fined by the homage, the third part of which fine ſhalbe to the Lord, and the other two parts ſhal come to him in the reuercion or remainder of the ſaid copihold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>51 Item,</hi> The Lord for non paiment of amerciaments, may diſtraine his ſaid Tenaunts, and auow for the ſame as for rents, but he can not ſeaze any of his or their lands or tenements for non pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, vntill he be paide.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21650:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>52 Item,</hi> vppon the admiſſion of any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heires, ioynt Tenaunts, or Tenaunts in common, if they cannot agree to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie their Landes and Tenements to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, or to make particion among them ſelues, then he or they that be greeued may by the cuſtome of euerie of the ſaide mannours haue a precept from the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward directed to ſeauen cuſtomarie Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunts or more of the ſaide Mannours, within which the ſaid Lands and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements doe lye, and they ſhall make particion thereof, and the ſame returne to the Steward of the ſaid Mannours againe to be inroled in the Court Roles of the ſaide Mannours, whereof the ſaid Landes or Tenements be holden, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon the ſaide heires ſhall goe to the Steward of the ſaide Mannours with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in which the ſaid Lands or Teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, ſhall lye, and then elcte and chuſe their partes in forme following. That is to ſaie, the youngeſt ſonne to chuſe firſt, then he that is next to the youngeſt to chuſe next, and ſo after that rate vnto the eldeſt, howe manie ſo euer, which eldeſt ſhall chuſe laſt, and likewiſe the ſame order is to bee obſerued amongeſt
<pb facs="tcp:21650:22"/> daughters, if there be no ſonnes. And amongeſt all other degrees of heires touching the cuſtomarie Landes and Tenements holden of the ſaide Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours or either of them, and vpon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſuch particion, they ſhall paie for a fine to the Lord, ii. s. vi. d. or leſſe, at the diſcretion of the Steward, according to the quantitie of the Landes or Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements ſo parted, betweene Tenaunts in common, &amp; ioynte Tenaunts, for the like fine, the ſaide deuiſion to bee by the ſaide Tenaunts without election of the parties themſelues, but by caſting of Lottes, if they cannot otherwiſe agree.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>53 Item,</hi> if any cuſtomarie or free te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunts cattell, or the cattels of their far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours be brought to the Lordes pound, the ſaide Tenaunt or his farmour ſhall paie for all his Cattell if they be a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred heddes or vpwards, or vnder, for the poundage therof but one peny, &amp; he that is no tenaunt ſhall pay for euery diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres of cattel ſo pounded foure pence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>54 Item,</hi> if any cattel be impounded with in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords pound by any perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s being a cuſtomary tenaunt or tenaunts
<pb facs="tcp:21650:23"/> of the ſaide Mannours or of either of them for any treſpas committed or done within the ſaide Mannours, or in either of them, vppon their coppiholds, that all ſuch Cattell being ſo impownded, maye by two of the cuſtomary tenaunts of the ſaid Mannours or of either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſaide Treſpas ſhalbe committed, which wil aunſwer for all ſuch damags and coſts as ſhalbe recouered in the ſaid Court againſt the owners of the ſame Cattell, for the ſaide Treſpas, be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered out of the ſaide pownd vnto the owner of the ſaid Cattell, by the cuſtome of the ſame mannours, &amp; of either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>55 Item,</hi> by the cuſtome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid manors &amp; of either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no cuſtomary tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhal ſue, vex, or trouble anie other cuſtomarie Tenaunt, for anie title of Landes or Tenements lying and being within the ſaide Mannours or in either of them, being Coppihold Landes or tenements of the ſaide Mannours or of either of them, out of the Lordes Court, without the ſpeciall licence firſt had and obtained of the Lorde of the ſaid Mannours, or of either of them, or of his Steward for
<pb facs="tcp:21650:23"/> the time being, if any perſon doe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, he ſhall haue his Landes or tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes ſeized into the Lordes hands, vntill he pay a fine to the Lorde for the ſame offence, ſuch fine as ſhalbe ſeſſed by thomage at the next generall Court of the ſaide Mannour or Mannours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>56 Item,</hi> that no cuſtomary Tenaunt of the ſaide Mannours or of either of them for anie offence to be done by anie mannes Cattell within the ſaide Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, or in either of them, ſhall driue the ſame Cattel to any forraine pounds, but to the lords pound, being within the ſayd Mannours, or in either of them, if anie man doe the contrarie, to be amerced at the next generall court by the homage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>57 Item,</hi> that no tenaunt or any other perſon ſhal ſet any ſtake, mark or meare, betweene tenaunt and tenaunt, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Tenaunt and any other perſon that lyeth next vnto him, without the parties doe therevnto agree, vnleſſe an order be appointed by the Homage, that it may be firſt viewed by twelue tenants of the ſaide Mannours, or of either of
<pb facs="tcp:21650:24"/> them, where the ſtake or meare is to bee ſet, and there to ſet the ſtake or marke, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differentlie betweene both the ſaide par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſo to continew it vpon paine of amerciament by the homage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>58 Item,</hi> by the cuſtome, the homage do yeerelie vſe at the generall Court hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den after Lowe Sunday, to elect and chuſe out of the hamlets within euirie of the ſaid Mannours, certaine cuſtomary Tenaunts to be driuers and viewers of the waſts and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons of the ſaid Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours or of either of them for one whole yeere, which haue authoritie by the ſaid Cuſtome to driue the commons at anie time when they finde it ſurcharged, and to impound the Cattell by them ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and no other ſo to driue the ſaide common, then the perſons ſo choſen as aforeſaide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>59 Item,</hi> if by their driuing the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging cannot be remedied, then they ought to informe the Homage thereof at the next Court, that they may amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce thoffenders, whether the ſaide offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders be Tenaunts or no Tenaunts, and
<pb facs="tcp:21650:24"/> alſo to put a paine or an amerciame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their heades, that they ſhall not likewiſe offend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>60 Item,</hi> if the ſaid driuers receiue by the ſaid poundages any more mony then they ſpend in their trauel, the reſt ſhalbe imployed to the Scowring of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſewers, which be vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaid waſt grounds &amp; commons, &amp; laying of bridges ouer the ſaide common ſewers, and ſhall make their accompt in that behalfe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> homage at the general court, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere for which they were choſen ſhall expire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>61 Item,</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſtome of the ſaid Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors &amp; of either of them, the coppieholde &amp; cuſtomary tenaunts haue vſed to make byelawes at their general courts when ned haue ſo required, which cuſtome ſhal be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued &amp; the ſaid bylawes ſo by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made, ſhall binde all the Coppiehold Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauns of the ſaid Mannours or of either of them, ſo the ſame bee not contrarie to the true meaning of theſe Articles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>62 Item,</hi> by the cuſtome of the ſaid man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors &amp; of either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tenaunts in taile of
<pb facs="tcp:21650:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> cuſtomarie Lands and tenements may ſuffer common recoueries within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid ſeuerall Mannors, with ſingle or double vouchers, or by agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t forfait the ſaid Lands and Tenements into the Lords hande for the cutting of the eſtate tayle, which cuſtome by theſe Articles ſhall hauc ſtill continuaunce, and that ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coueries &amp; forfaitures are &amp; ſhalbe good by the ſaide cuſtome to barre the ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Sealed and deliuered in the preſence of Edmond Poley, Iohn Lany, Thomas Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kelin, Thomas Kent, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Onſlow, Iohn Iermy.</dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21650:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
